Finding Aid for Charles Rasch Collection, 1890-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Rasch Collection 1890-2011, 1953-2005
Rasch, Charles.
1 oversized folder
4 linear feet (in 6 boxes)
24 oversize volumes
2011157 Aa 2; UAm
Charles ("Charlie") Rasch was a professional pianist, talented photographer, and graduate of the University of Michigan. The collection contains scrapbooks, photographs, and negatives documenting his life in Michigan. The majority of photographs and negatives are labeled with the date and location.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Howard and Rose Rasch (donor no. 10655 ) in October 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
A native of Birmingham, MI, Charles ("Charlie") Rasch was a ragtime pianist, artist, and talented nature photographer. He received both his BA and MA from the University of Michigan, and served two years in the U.S. Army.
The Charles Rasch Collection (23 oversize volumes and 5 linear feet) is primarily composed of photographs and negatives documenting Michigan scenery. There is particularly strong coverage of Birmingham, MI, Harsen's Island, MI, the Island Lake Recreation Area in Brighton, MI, and the Bald Mountain Recreation Area in Oakland, MI. Many of these photographs, especially his early black and white work, display his artistic training and sensibilities. Rasch's scrapbooks also offer a rich representation of the ragtime music scene in Michigan and the Ann Arbor area. This collection is also notable for the care Rasch took to annotate his photographs. Many negatives and prints are individually labeled, and all include some information relating to the date and location.
The collection has been arranged in the following series: Scrapbooks and Albums, Papers, Individual Photographs, Photographs, and Photographic Negatives.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Rasch, Charles.; Musicians--Michigan.; Nature--Michigan.; Rivers--Michigan.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Bald Mountain Recreation Area (Mich.); Birmingham (Mich.); Harsen's Island (Mich.); Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Island Lake State Recreation Area (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Black-and-white negatives.; Color negatives.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Scrapbooks and Albums
  The Scrapbooks and Albums (23 oversized volumes and 0.5 linear feet) series is composed primarily of scrapbooks compiled by Rasch, in addition to a family album and an album of photographs of passenger ferries collected by Rasch. The scrapbooks contain clippings, photographs, and ephemera. The scrapbooks contain items relating to Rasch's time at the University of Michigan and his career in music.
  - Blue Water District 1953-2008, 23 volumes
    - Blue Water District 1953 (Volume 1)
    - 1954 (Volume 2)
    - 1955 (Volume 3)
    - 1956 (Volume 4)
    - 1957 (Volume 5)
    - 1958 (Volume 6)
    - 1960 (Volume 7)
    - 1964 (Volume 8)
    - 1965 (Volume 9)
    - 1966 (Volume 24)
    - 1968 (Volume 10)
    - 1975-1979 (Volume 11)
    - 1980-1984 (Volume 12)
    - 1985-1989 (Volume 13)
    - 1990-1991 (Volume 14)
    - 1992-1993 (Volume 15)
    - 1994-1995 (Volume 16)
    - 1996-1997 (Volume 17)
    - 1998-1999 (Volume 18)
    - 2000-2003 (Volume 19)
    - 2004-2005 (Volume 20)
    - 2006-2007 (Volume 21)
    - 2008 (Volume 22)
    - Cabin (Volume 23)
  - Family Photograph Album circa 1890 (Box 1)
  - Passenger Ferry Album (Box 1)
- Papers
  The Papers (0.2 linear feet) series contains biographical material on Rasch and genealogical material on the Rasch family.
  - An Alphabet of Nature 2010 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Federation of Musicians 1994 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Postcard 1914 (Box 1)
  - Christmas Card 1987 (Box 1)
  - Commission to Colonelcy 1928 (Box 1)
    (see oversized folder)
  - Descendants of Florian Rasch I 2003 (Box 1)
  - Frog Sketch circa 1975 (Box 1)
  - Obituary 2011 (Box 1)
  - Ragtime Down the Trail (Box 1)
  - Soft Turtles Print 1898 (Box 1)
- Individual Photographs
  (formerly framed with Rash's identification)
  The Individual Photographs (0.7 linear feet) series contains photographs that originally came to the library framed. All photographs are labeled with the date and information relating to the subject and the location of the photograph. Many also include information on the process Rasch used to frame them. The photographs have been removed from their frames for storage purposes.
  - Family Portraits undated
    - Allen Arthur Rasch (Box 1)
    - Charles Andrew Rasch (Box 1)
  - Robert William Rasch (Box 1)
  - View of Harsen's Island 1898 (Box 1)
  - Allen Rich Rasch on Harsen's Island, MI circa 1925 (Box 1)
  - Petoskey Street (Harsen's Island, MI) 1957 (Box 1)
  - Steward Road Bridge (Harsen's Island, MI) 1958 (Box 1)
  - Frank Rasch Cottage 1959 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Canoe Livery 1960 (Box 1)
  - Ken and Carole on the Huron River 1960 (Box 1)
  - Kate and Me 1964 (Box 1)
  - Theodore Vernon Stein II 1964 (Box 1)
  - Whoopee Bridge Over Snooks Highway (Harsen's Island, MI) 1966 (Box 1)
  - Joe Foder's Riverboat Shufflers at the Anchor Inn (Portage, MI) 1970 (Box 1)
  - Kate and Me at the Ann Arbor Moose Club 1972 (Box 1)
  - Huron River Across from the Poison Ivy Camp 1973 (Box 1)
  - Huron River North of Dexter at the Rock Dam 1973 (Box 1)
  - Canoeing at the Arch 1974 (Box 1)
  - Huron River (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1977 (Box 1)
  - Gossamer by the Road to Trout Lake 1989 (Box 1)
  - Footbridge (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1990 (Box 1)
  - Footbridge on the Orange Trail (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1990 (Box 1)
  - Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1990 (Box 1)
  - Blue Trail (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1991 (Box 1)
  - Blazing Star Near Trout Lake 1992 (Box 1)
  - Huron River (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1992 (Box 1)
  - The Big Oak by the Trail (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 1)
  - Blue Trail (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 1)
  - Footbridge (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 1)
  - Huron River (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 1)
  - Mullein-Rosette (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 1)
  - October Blue and Gold (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 1)
  - Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 1)
  - White Trail (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 1)
  - Ant Hills (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1994 (Box 1)
  - Coffee Rock (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1994 (Box 1)
  - East Graham Lake Footbridge 1994 (Box 1)
  - Prairie Dock 1994 (Box 1)
  - Queen Anne's Lace (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1994 (Box 1)
  - Footbridge (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1995 (Box 1)
  - New Footbridge (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1995 (Box 1)
  - Chief Pontiac Trail Footbridge (Proud Lake Recreation Area) 1996 (Box 1)
  - Lunaria Seed Discs 1997 (Box 1)
  - Mayapples (Kensington Metropark) 1997 (Box 1)
  - Rivulet flowing under the Red Trail (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1997 (Box 1)
  - Trillium by the Red Trail (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1997 (Box 1)
  - Milkweed (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1998 (Box 1)
  - Milkweed (Island Lake Recreation Area) 2003 (Box 1)
  - Linda's Backyard (Birmingham, MI) 2005 (Box 1)
  - White Oak on the Hill (Kensington Metropark) 2005 (Box 1)
  - At the Canada Club (St. Clair River) 1953 (Box 2)
  - Tashmoo Dock 1953 (Box 2)
    see oversized folder
  - The Lady S. on the Canadian March (Harsen's Island, MI) 1956 (Box 2)
  - The Lady S. at Uphalls (Harsen's Island, MI) 1959 (Box 2)
  - Canal on Green Drive (Harsen's Island, MI) 1967 (Box 2)
  - Huron River Just Below Barton Dam 1967 (Box 2)
  - Camp on Norton Creek 1973 (Box 2)
  - Huron River Across from the Poison Ivy Camp 1973 (Box 2)
  - Huron River Below McCabe Road Bridge 1973 (Box 2)
  - Huron River 1974 (Box 2)
  - Huron River Near Dexter 1974 (Box 2)
  - Huron River (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1979 (Box 2)
  - John Hester on the middle Branch River (Osceola County, MI) 1984 (Box 2)
  - Hornet's Nest (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1989 (Box 2)
  - Huron River (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1990 (Box 2)
  - Footbridge Over Mann Creek (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1991 (Box 2)
  - On the Loop Trail Near Placeway Road (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1991 (Box 2)
  - Trout Lake Northeast End (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1991 (Box 2)
  - Footbridge Over the Creek (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1992 (Box 2)
  - Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1992 (Box 2)
  - Huron River (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 2)
  - Trail North of the Huron (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 2)
  - Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1993 (Box 2)
  - Huron River (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1994 (Box 3)
  - Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1994 (Box 3)
  - Huron River Just Below the Kent Lake Dam (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1995 (Box 3)
  - Looking Down the Huron by Mann Creek (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1995 (Box 3)
  - River Trip -- Looking Down the Huron River (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1995 (Box 3)
  - Road to Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1996 (Box 3)
  - Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1996 (Box 3)
  - Looking North on the Red Trail (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1997 (Box 3)
  - Looking Up the Huron (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1997 (Box 3)
  - Sunset by the Road to Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 1997 (Box 3)
  - Blue Trail Near Point Five (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1998 (Box 3)
  - Looking Down the Blue Line Trail (Bald Mountain Recreation Area) 1999 (Box 3)
  - Looking West on the Trail South of the Huron (Island Lake Recreation Area 1999 (Box 3)
  - Trout Lake (Island Lake Recreation Area) 2000 (Box 3)
  - Huron River Trip (Island Lake Recreation Area) 2003 (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs (1 linear foot) series includes photographs taken by Rasch between 1988 and 2005. The majority of the photographs are of wildlife. The series also includes a number of family photographs from the 1930s and 1940s.
  - Family Photographs circa 1937-1942 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Portraits undated (Box 3)
  - Photograph Wallets (Milford Area) 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - 1988 (Box 4)
  - 1989 (Box 4)
  - 1990 (Box 4)
  - 1991, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 1992, 3 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 1993, 3 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 1994, 4 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 1995, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 1996, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 1997, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 1998 (Box 4)
  - 1999, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 2000 (Box 4)
  - 2000-2001, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 2002 (Box 4)
  - 2003, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 2004, 2 envelopes (Box 4)
  - 2005, 3 envelopes (Box 4)
- Photograph Negatives
  The Photographic Negatives (2 linear feet) series makes up the bulk of the collection and includes both black and white and color negatives of photographs taken by Rasch. The series is arranged chronologically, and thereunder by subject or location. Many negatives have been individually labeled by Rasch.
  - Mill's Pharmacy Candy Counter 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - "The New Old Family Album"
    - Allen R. Rasch Family Christmas 1937 (Box 5)
    - Birmingham (Box 5)
    - Birmingham (color) (Box 5)
    - Charles A. Rasch Bus Station Photo (Box 5)
    - Detroit 1953 (Box 5)
    - Large Size Negatives (Box 5)
    - Neighborhood Views 1953, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Standard and Small Size Negatives (Box 5)
  - 1953
    - Algonac (Box 5)
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Anchor Bay Area (Box 5)
    - Canada (Box 5)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 5)
    - Marine City (Box 5)
    - New Baltimore (Box 5)
    - Port Huron (Box 5)
    - River Boat (Box 5)
    - St. Clair (Box 5)
    - St. Clair Flats (Box 5)
  - 1954
    - Algonac (Box 5)
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Anchor Bay (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area, 2 envelopes (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (color) (Box 5)
    - Christmas (Box 5)
    - Detroit and Area (Box 5)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 5)
    - Marine City (Box 5)
    - River Boat (Box 5)
    - St. Clair (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - 1955
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area, 2 envelopes (Box 5)
    - Birmingham High School Washington Trip, 3 envelopes (Box 5)
    - Christmas (Box 5)
    - College Days (Box 5)
    - Colored Photographs (Box 5)
    - Detroit and Area (Box 5)
    - Harsen' Island (Box 5)
    - Senior Skip Day -- Camp Ohiyesa Fish Lake (Holly, MI) July 6, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Sue Allen's Party -- Fenton Lake July 17, 1955 (Box 5)
  - 1956
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 5)
    - College Days (Box 5)
    - Detroit and Area (Box 5)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 5)
    - Railroad Excursion (Greenville, MI) September 1956 (Box 5)
  - 1957
    - Along the Road, 2 envelopes (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (Color and Black and White) (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 5)
    - College Days (color) (Box 5)
    - College Days (Box 5)
    - Detroit and Area (Box 5)
    - End of the Semester (Box 5)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 5)
    - Railroad Excursion (Stratford Ontario) September 1957 (Box 5)
    - Trip to New Hampshire and Dartmouth College (Box 5)
    - Trip to New Hampshire and Dartmouth College (color) (Box 5)
  - 1958
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 5)
    - Chicago (Box 5)
    - College Days (Box 5)
    - Color Negatives (Box 5)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 5)
    - Merrill Palmer Camp, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Railroad Excursion (Pigeon, MI) (Box 5)
    - Small Negatives (color and black and white)
      - College Days (Box 5)
      - Along the Road (Box 5)
  - 1959
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 5)
    - College Days (Box 5)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 5)
    - Merrill Palmer Camp (Box 5)
    - Small photograph negatives (Box 5)
    - Term Paper House Negatives (Box 5)
    - The Three Graces at Home (Ann Arbor) (Box 5)
  - 1960
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 5)
    - College Days (Box 5)
    - Colored Photograph Negatives (Box 5)
    - Harsens Island (Box 5)
    - Gravestones (Box 5)
  - 1961
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 5)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 5)
  - 1964
    - Along the Road (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 5)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 5)
    - Black and White Small Negatives (Box 5)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 5)
    - Ragtime Charlie and Sister Kate (Box 5)
  - 1965
    - Along the Road (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 6)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 6)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 6)
  - 1966
    - Along the Road (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 6)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 6)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 6)
  - 1967
    - Along the Road (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 6)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 6)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 6)
    - Panorama of Harsen's Island October 12, 1967 (Box 6)
  - 1968
    - 4th of July (Box 6)
    - 10 Years Later (Box 6)
    - Along the Road (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 6)
    - Ann Arbor (People) (Box 6)
    - Birmingham and Area (Box 6)
    - Harsen's Island (Box 6)
    - Joe and Sandie Knollenberg's Party July 1968 (Box 6)
    - Labor Day Weekend (Bay City) (Box 6)
    - Visit with Wilbur and Loretta Jacobs (Torch Lake) August 1968 (Box 6)
  - 1973-1989
    - Along the Road and River 1973 (Box 6)
    - Old Bridges 1976
      - Belle River (Box 6)
      - Huron River (Box 6)
      - Saline River (Box 6)
      - River Raisin (Box 6)
    - Hester's Cabin 1977 (Box 6)
    - Huron River Camping Trip and New Huron Street Bridge 1977 (Box 6)
    - Rouge River, Linden Park, Birmingham and Camp Boxes 1978 (Box 6)
    - Hester's Cabin and Huron River 1979 (Box 6)
    - 1983 (Box 6)
    - 1984 (Box 6)
    - Bray's Cabin 1985 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1988, 2 envelopes (Box 6)
    - Bald Mountain and Island Lake State Recreation Areas 1988 (Box 6)
    - Views of Garden (7) 1989 (Box 6)
    - Bald Mountain State Recreation Area 1989 (Box 6)
    - My Wildflower Garden 1989 (Box 6)
    - Trout Lake and Miscellaneous 1989, 4 envelopes (Box 6)
  - 1990-2005
    - 1990, 11 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1991, 13 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1992, 14 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1993, 17 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1994, 16 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1995, 10 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1996, 10 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1997, 13 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1998, 8 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 1999, 12 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 2000, 8 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 2001, 8 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 2002, 8 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 2003, 12 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 2004, 12 envelopes (Box 6)
    - 2005, 14 envelopes (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Tombstone Negatives 1962 (Box 6)
    - Harsen's Island Historical Photographs and Negatives (Box 6)
    - Postcards, 2 envelopes (Box 6)
    - Sister Kate in her Flapper Costumes 1971 (Box 6)
    - Mill's Pharmacy Candy Counter 1955-1956 (Box 6)